Guide to the Thomas A. Rabson academic papers, 1950-2000 MS 558
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Thomas A. Rabson academic papers
1950-2000
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rabson, Thomas A.
MS 558
3 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
This collection contains correspondence, departmental records, course preparation materials, and course assistant records relating to Thomas A. Rabson's career as professor of electrical engineering at Rice University. Also included are conference materials, reference materials, energy research studies and reports, and information concerning Dr. Rabson's grant proposals, consultation with energy and electronics corporations, and expertise in lasers and ferroelectric thin films.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas A. Rabson was born in Houston, TX on July 31, 1932 and graduate from Lamar High School in 1950. He attended Rice University from 1950 to 1959, earning a Bachelor of Art, Bachelor of Science in Electrical Engineering, Master of Arts in Physics, and Doctor of Philosophy in Physics. Dr. Rabson joined the Rice faculty in 1959 and built the Ph.D program for Electrical Engineering, graduating the first doctoral student in his department. He served as professor of electrical engineering from 1970-2000 and was chairman of the department from 1979-1984. He was an active member of IEEE, the American Physical Society, the Optical Society of America, and the Society of Photo-Optical Instrumentation Engineers. Additionally, he was a Rice representative on the U.S. Council for Energy Awareness and a consultant of a number of energy, electronics, and geophysical corporations, including Shell Oil Company, Exxon USA, Texas Instruments, Inc., and Motorola, Inc. He is also a member of Tau Beta Pi, Sigma Tau, and Sigma Xi and served as a National Science Foundation Science Faculty Fellow in Basel, Switzerland from 1965-1966.He has received such honors as Who's Who in the Southwest, American Men of Science, and program manager of Project Thesis Research at Rice University from 1968-1973. Dr. Rabson retired from Rice University after earning emeritus status in May 2000 and moved to Madisonville, Texas. He is widely recognized for his pioneering work in the field of lasers and his expertise on ferroelectric thin films and the properties and uses of lithium niobate.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, departmental records, course preparation materials, and course assistant records relating to Thomas A. Rabson's career as professor of electrical engineering at Rice University. Also included are conference materials, reference materials, energy research studies and reports, and information concerning Dr. Rabson's grant proposals, consultation with energy and electronics corporations and expertise in lasers and ferroelectric thin films.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Mrs. Thomas A. Rabson in 2009.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges; Engineering; Education; Authors
Document Types
notes; corrrespondence; photographs; reports; syllabi
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University
- Series I: Biographical and personal, 1950-1961, undated; 109179
  - Thomas A. Rabson: Biographical information, 109180 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of TAR, undated, 109181 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - TAR: Selective Service forms, 109182 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - European travel, 1961, 109183 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Panoramic class photo of Lamar High School, 195o, Houston, Texas, 109184 (Map-drawer 33)
- Series II: Academic coursework and publications, 109185
  - TAR: Report on sabbatical leave, 109186 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - TAR: Academics, 109187 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - TAR: Resume notes and materials, 109188 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - TAR: Honors, 109189 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Honor society pins, 109190 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Messages and phone numbers, 109191 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Punch cards, 109192 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Receipts and expenses, 1960-1969, undated, 109193 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence to TAR, 109194 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence from TAR, 109195 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence to and from Sylvia Rabson, 109196 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Letters of recommendation, 109197 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Rice University, 109198 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence to TAR re: salary, 109199 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Rice University envelopes, 109200 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Rice University Self Study Summary Report, 1964, 109201 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "University Policies of Interest to the Faculty", January, 1967, 109202 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Rice University newsletters, 1975, 109203 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Rice University programs and directory, 109204 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Engineering dept. goals, 1984, 109205 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Electrical Engineering/Computer Science enrollment increase communication, 109206 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence re: Electrical Engineering departmental concerns, 109207 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Electrical Engineering departmental concerns (3 folders), 109208 (Box 1, Folder 27-29)
  - Electrical Engineering salary information, 109209 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Grade book for E.E. 460, 473, 543 and 561, 1959-64, 109210 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Electrical Engineering teaching schedules, 1965-1966, 109211 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - ELEC 561 class notes, Spring 1971, 109212 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - ELEC 362 class notes, Fall 1971, 109213 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - ELEC 462 class notes, Spring 1980, 109214 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - ELEC 461 class notes, Fall 1981, Fall 1982, 109215 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - ELEC 463 class notes, Spring 1982, 109216 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - ELEC 342 class notes, Spring 1986, 109217 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - ELEC 461 class notes, Fall 1986, 109218 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - ELEC 461 class notes, Fall 1987, 109220 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - ELEC 461 class notes, Fall 1987, Fall 1988, 109219 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - ELEC 342 class notes and roster, Spring 1988, 109221 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - ELEC 305b class notes, Spring 1991, 109222 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - ELEC 461 class notes, Fall 1991, 109223 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - ELEC 591 class notes, Fall 1991, 109224 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - ELEC 591 class notes, Spring 1994, 109225 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Student work, 109226 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Assorted class notes, 109227 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Unlabeled notes and handouts, 109228 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Answer keys, 109229 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Transparencies on ferroelectrics and LiNbO3 thin films, 109230 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Impedance Measurement Tutorial" transparencies, 2000, 109231 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Electrical Engineering Graduate Committee Report, 1971-72, 109232 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Graduate student information, 109233 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Roster of Computer Science majors, Fall 1983, 109234 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Computer Science class roster, Fall 1983, 109235 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Course assistant materials, undated, 109236 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Course assistant records, Spring 1967, 109237 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Course assistant records, Fall 1967, 109238 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Course assistant records, Spring 1968, 109239 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Course assistant records, Fall 1968, 109240 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Course assistant records, Spring 1969, 109241 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Course assistant records, Fall 1969, 109242 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Course assistant records, Spring 1970, 109243 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Course assistant records, Fall 1970, 109244 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Course assistant records, Spring 1971, 109245 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Course assistant records, Fall 1971, 109246 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Course assistant records, Spring 1972, 109247 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Advisory Report on Engineering Education in Texas, 1968, 109248 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Energy Courses Initiative, 1974, 109249 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Microelectronics programs at other universities, 109250 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - U.S. News "Best Colleges" issue, October 10, 1988, 109251 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Grant application materials, 109252 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - NASA grant, 1960-1967, 109253 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Grant proposal: "Study of MASERS and Their Application", March 31, 1961, 109254 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Microelectronics laboratory notes and proposals, 109255 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Laser Handbook proposal, 109256 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - William P. Jenny patent application, 1953, 109257 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Consulting notes, 109258 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Legal pad notes, 109259 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Semiconductor Research Corporation, 109260 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Technical Enterprises Corporation, 109261 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Texas Instruments: Texas Advanced Technology Program, 109262 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Atomic Industrial Forum: 1969 Annual Meeting, 109263 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Atomic Industrial Forum: University/Industry Relations Committee, 109264 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Atomic Industrial Forum: Newsletters and brochures, 109265 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Conference programs, 1970, 1973, 109266 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Symposium on Integrated Ferroelectrics, 1990, 1992, 109267 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Texas Energy Development Fund grant proposal submission guidelines, 109268 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Energy related research reports for Texas legislature, 109269 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Energy Research and Development Administration (ERDA) reports, 109270 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Energy Research and Education Foundation (EREF): Energy info, 109271 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - EREF: Board of Directors meeting notes, 109272 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - EREF: Administrative info, 109273 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - EREF: Rice Seminar Series, 109274 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - EREF: Monthly energy facts, 109275 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - EREF: Remarks of N.J. Tortorello, February 1, 1977, 109276 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - EREF: Vendors, 109277 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Energy Interests: RANN Conference, May 28, 1975, 109278 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Energy Interests: Advanced studies and research, 109279 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Energy Interests: Brochures and advertisements, 109280 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Energy Interests: Reports and publications, 109281 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Interactions of Electromagnetic Radiation with Matter in the Solid State", paper unsigned and undated, 109282 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Informational pamphlets c.1950s, 1968, 109283 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Notebook: "Acoustic Wave Systems", text pp. 23-28, 109284 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Notebook: Notes on Microwave Theory, 109285 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Dresser Electronics, 109286 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - K&E Log Log Duplex Vector Slide Rule manual, 109287 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Place Tables of Logarithms and Trigonometric Functions, 109288 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Nuclear Energy Institute InfoBank, 109289 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Publications: Physics Letters, August 25, 1969, 109290 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Publications: "Determination of Conduction Anisotropies in Semiconductors", 1971, 109291 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Publications: "Ferroelectric Gate Transfers" drafts, 109292 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Publications: Published works, 1995-1999, 109293 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Model Train Layout No. 1, 109294 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Photographs,1950, undated, 109295 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Optical crystals (5 folders), 109296 (Box 3, Folder 29-33)
  - Retirement proclamation to Rabson by Sidney Burrus, 109297 (Map-drawer 33)